Guide to the Lionel Trilling Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Lionel Trilling Papers,
1899-1987
Trilling, Lionel, 1905-1975.
27 linear feet (51 document boxes, 3 index card boxes)
Columbia University, Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY, 10027.
MS#1256
4079615
The Lionel Trilling Papers document the life of author, professor, and literary critic, Lionel Trilling. This collection contains his writings, extensive correspondence with other New York intellectuals, personal documents, and other records concerning his professional activities.
Biographical Note
Lionel Trilling was an intellectual force in the New York literary and political scene throughout much of the 20th Century. A prolific writer, Trilling published literary criticism and cultural commentaries in journals such as The Nation, Commentary, The New York Times, The New York Times Book Review, and The Menorah Journal. Some of these publications were created by Trilling's colleagues, a group of left-leaning, Anti-Stalinist critics and theorists the New York Intellectuals like Daniel Bell, Irving Howe, Alfred Kazin, and Sidney Hook. These individuals were predominantly Jewish men who established themselves as a kind of “American Bloomsbury” to quote Columbia University professor of journalism Nicholas Lemann. Outside of his writing, Trilling was a popular and respected professor of English Literature at Columbia University. Together, with historian Jacques Barzun, Trilling helped to establish some of the core interdisciplinary classes that were vital to the growth and development of Columbia as a competitive academic environment.
Lionel M. Trilling was born on July 4, 1905 in New York City to businessman David W. Trilling and his wife Fannie (neé Cohen). As a child, Trilling attended DeWitt Clinton High School in the Bronx where he was a colleague of Countee Cullen. At school Trilling participated as a member of the Book Review Squad, the Reporters Squad, and president of Papyrus. He also wrote for the school publication, Magpie as well as co-authored a class play. In 1921 Lionel Trilling entered Columbia University, an institution that was to be his intellectual home for the rest of his life. Trilling graduated from Columbia with his A.B. in 1925 and his M.A. in 1926. For the next eleven years Trilling worked toward a doctorate in English Literature. However, this path was interrupted by work. He did not complete the Ph.D. until 1938.
Trilling left New York to be an Instructor of English at the University of Wisconsin from 1926 to 1927. Upon his return, Trilling began to date a recent Radcliffe graduate named Diana Rubin. Rubin was also a New Yorker, having been brought up in Manhattan. She briefly worked with her mother, Cecelia, as an interior designer while she pursued a career as a classical singer. Illness forced Rubin to abandon that goal. She and Lionel married on October 25, 1929.
A couple of years later, Trilling began teaching at Columbia University. His initial position was as an instructor and in 1939 he was made an assistant professor. From 1939 until 1944 he held this position and was promoted in 1944 to associate professor. Trilling was the first Jewish professor in the department to receive tenure. Throughout his career, Trilling was extremely involved with his undergraduate students. Along with his colleague and close friend, Jacques Barzun, Trilling reinstated a series of interdisciplinary or “general education” courses. With Barzun, Trilling taught a portion of the course entitled, Colloquium on Important Books, in which he covered cultural history and criticism of the 19th and 20th centuries. In 1969, Trilling was given the title of University Professor, a post he held until his retirement from teaching in 1975.
Although he was an active faculty member, Trilling published quite regularly. His dissertation, Matthew Arnold, was published a year after he completed the degree. This was followed by another study, E.M. Forster in 1943. Other publications include a novel, The Middle of the Journey (1949), several volumes of short stories; the most well-known of these is Of This Time, Of That Place (1940). However, Trilling is best known for his collections of critical essays, in particular The Liberal Imagination (1950), The Opposing Self (1955), and Beyond Culture (1965). Trilling was interested in Sigmund Freud as a cultural icon as well as using Freudian psychology in the analysis of literature. Two books that focused on these themes were Freud and the Crisis of Our Culture (1955) and The Life and Work of Sigmund Freud (1962). Please note that Trilling's writings encompassed decades of work and that countless bibliographies have been attempted and often abandoned due to the sheer size of his oeuvre.
Trilling did not spend all of his time strictly at Columbia. He was a founder, with John Crowe Ransom and F.O. Matthiessen, of the Kenyon School of Letters, now referred to as The School of Letters, Indiana University. Beginning in 1951 as a summer program, the school expanded to a full-year program in 1961, with a focus on literary theory and criticism. Information concerning The School of Letters may be found in the Indiana University School of Letters Director's Records finding aid located in the Indiana University Archives.
Throughout his life, Lionel Trilling maintained a high level of professional achievement and this was reflected in the many academic accolades he received. He served as the George Eastman Visiting Professor at Oxford University from 1964-1965. There, Trilling lectured at the university and other academic and intellectual institutions as well as taught classes. He was accompanied by Diana Trilling who, by this time, had firmly established herself as a serious literary and cultural critic and penned for a variety of journals, including Partisan Review, The New York Times Book Review, Redbook, The Nation, The New Leader, and McCall's. She had also recently published a book entitled, Claremont Essays. They were joined by their son, James Lionel Trilling. He was born in 1949 and at that point was a student at Exeter.
Four years later, Trilling was the Charles Eliot Norton Visiting Professor at Harvard University. In addition to these two positions, he held honorary doctorates from Trinity College in Hartford Connecticut (1955), Harvard University (1962), Case Western Reserve University in Cleveland Ohio (1968), Northwestern University (1963), Leicester University (1973), Brandeis University (1974) and Yale University (1974). Trilling was awarded the Alexander Hamilton Medal from Brandeis University in 1968 and gave the first annual Jefferson Lecture for the National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH) in 1972. He was a Guggenheim Fellow from 1948 to 1949 and received a second grant that he was unable to use in 1975.
While he was active in his field, Trilling was a member of the Modern Language Association, the American Committee for Cultural Freedom of which both he and Diana Trilling resigned once the organization redirected its mission, The National Institute of Arts and Letters, and The American Academy of Arts and Sciences.
As the 1960s unfolded, student unrest grew on American campuses, in particular Kent State and Columbia University. Although Trilling was teaching at that time, he, like most members of the faculty, was unaware of the growing dissatisfaction among the students and the community of Harlem. Always considered a driving force behind New York intellectualism, he would later be criticized for never publicly recognizing the importance of the social movements that occurred during the decade as well as the racial components that were driving the majority of them.
Upon his retirement from Columbia, Trilling was awarded the title of Professor Emeritus. Shortly after, he was taken ill with a fast moving form of cancer that had progressed undetected for too long. By November of that year, he had died. Diana Trilling published a twelve-volume set of his writings from 1977 to 1979. She also wrote The Beginning of the Journey: The Marriage of Diana and Lionel Trilling, a memoir of the first years of their life together. Diana Trilling died of cancer in October of 1996.
Scope and Content
The Lionel Trilling Papers document the professional work and personal life of Lionel Trilling (1905-1975), the prolific literary critic and Columbia University Professor of English Literature. This collection was acquired upon his death in 1975.
The bulk of the records consist of his many writings in the form of articles, essays, lectures, short stories, and book reviews. Correspondence with other prominent writers and intellectuals of the 20th century, family members, editors and publishers comprises the second largest series in the collection. Also contained are records concerning Trilling's work as a professor at Columbia University, as well as his involvement in various outside professional organizations. There is a small amount of personal documents and articles about Trilling's life and writings, including his detailed journals, comprised of his personal thoughts and intellectual queries.
Some of the items in this collection were originally located in the archives of his wife, Diana Trilling. Since their personal and professional lives intersected constantly, records concerning him, such as photographs and correspondence with his publishers, may be found in her collection as well.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in six series and seven subseries.
Series I: Personal, 1899-1975
Subseries I.1: Documents, 1899-1975
Subseries I.2: Journals, 1926-1975
Series II: Correspondence, 1900-1983
Subseries II.1: Alphabetical, 1900-1983
Subseries II.2: Chronological, 1925-1976
Series III: Writings, 1925-1974
Subseries III.1: Manuscripts and Papers, 1931-1975
Subseries III.2: Articles and Essays, 1925-1974
Subseries III.3: Notes, 1952-1974
Series IV: Professional Work, 1926-1987
Series V: Photographs, 1905-1963
Series VI: Realia, 1905-1971
Subjects
Columbia University.; Barzun, Jacques, 1907-; Ginsberg, Allen, 1926-1997.; Ransom, John Crowe, 1888-1974.; Trilling, Diana.; Van Doren, Mark, 1894-1972.; Authors, American--20th century.; American literature--20th century.; College teachers as authors--New York (State)--New York.; Criticism--United States.; Literary quarrels.; Articles.; Audio tapes.; Card files.; Journals.; Manuscripts (literary).; Photographs.; College teachers.; Critics.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located on-site.
There are two folders in Series IV: Professional Work that contain student grades and reference letters. These items are restricted until 2036 and 2040.
Gift of Lionel Trilling, 1966.
Gift of Diana Trilling, 1985-1995.
Gift of Edwin H. Miller, 1989.
Gift of Grover C. Smith, 1997.
Related Material
Diana Trilling Papers, 1921-1996
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library
MS#1421 http:www.columbia.edu/cu/lweb/archival/collections/ldpd_6259383/index.html
- Series I: Personal Papers, 1899-1975
  Series I holds some of Lionel Trilling's personal items. This small series has been arranged into two subseries: Documents and Journals. Academic records, biographical information, certificates, and other general personal documents are found in Subseries 1. Subseries 2 contains extensive personal writings, ranging from the mid-1920s to the end of Trilling's life. Subseries 1 is arranged by topic, while Subseries 2 is arranged chronologically. Family and personal photographs are located in Series V.
  - Subseries I.1: Documents, 1899-1975
    This small subseries is composed of Lionel Trilling’s personal items. Academic records, such as report cards from Columbia, the DeWitt Clinton High School yearbook and other publications featuring Trilling as a student, and essays written for his English classes at Columbia are found here. Other personal documents include a representative sample of his appointment books, a copy of the Trillings’ marriage license, early poems written for family members, several passports, and birth and death certificates. There are also a few items belonging to his mother, Fannie Trilling.
    - Academic Records, 1922-1928 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Address Book, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Appointment Books, 1957-1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Biographical Material, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Birth and Death Certificates, 1956, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Columbia University Assignments, 1921-1923 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Dewitt Clinton High School
      - Publications, 1920-1921 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Scrapbook, 1919-1921 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Yearbook, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Early Writings, undated, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Funeral Program, 1975 November 10 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Marriage Certificate, 1929 June 12 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Passports, 1956-1972 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Printed Material, 1918-1925 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Trilling, Fannie, 1899, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Subseries I.2: Journals, 1926-1975
    Trilling recalled his daily activities, including classes taught, events observed, and conversations conducted with colleagues, friends and family members. However, the journals are not limited to narrative. Trilling also jotted down hypotheses concerning life, literature, and, in particular, the relationship between men and women, as well as potential stories and essays. These diatribes ranged from the merely observant: "Is it a terrible struggle for a bird to fly? Has he always the imminent panic of falling?" to the profoundly theoretical:
    "There is one thing the world has immediate need of: I thought once it was a new religion but it is not that: it is that someone should ask a great thundering question-someone should ask it or the very earth should shout it, and the attentions of all to be turned to answer. We could not stand the certainty of a faith, I think. It is not at all necessary that the question be answered or answerable; it is only necessary that it be formulated and valid. But probably this is even more naively an impossible desire than for a new faith. What if I had only one question to answer?"
    And, occasionally, to the very personal:
    "Why do I so easily forget, and remember with so much surprise that one of the most intense and most un[scribbled word]edly passionate experiences I have had is the light of a scarlet leaved tree and that a flower can delight me? Why am I a little embarrassed to record this for myself?"
    Some of the journal entries have annotations that appear to have been added a later date by Diana Trilling. These notes clarify names or provide context for some of the entries. Some of the journals are clearly dated, albeit inconsistently, while others have approximated dates.
    - Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 1926 September-1929 Spring (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - 1930-1931 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - 1934-1936 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - 1938-1943 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Late 1930s-1940s (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Late 1930s-1941 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1944 October-1945 September 9 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 1945 September 9-1946 Summer (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - 1946 Summer-1948 September (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Late 1940s (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 1948 September-1952 April (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - 1952-1955 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Late 1950s-Late 1960s (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 1956 January-1957 October (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Circa 1958 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - 1958 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - 1959 March-1961 July (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - 1959 August 19-1963 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - 1960 March-August (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Sincerity and Authenticity, 1960s (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - 1963-1965 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - 1965 Fall-1968 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - 1967 December-1970 December (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - 1968 Fall (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - 1969-1970 ? (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - 1969-1971 ? (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - 1970-1974 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 1973 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - 1974 April (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1900-1983
  Series II holds Lionel Trilling's personal and professional correspondence. These letters were sent between Trilling and family members, colleagues at Columbia University and outside of the institution, contacts at publishing houses, and friends. This series is the largest in the collection and along with the writings, illuminates some of Trilling's opinions of other writers, developing literary trends, and the changing political situation, in particular World War II and the rise of social justice organizations in the 1960s. However, much of the correspondence consists of requests for Trilling to lecture, review new literary texts and give recommendations to former students and colleagues.
  The series has been arranged into two subseries: Alphabetical, by name or by topic, and Chronological. This collection was processed according to earlier manuscript processing standards followed; therefore letters of "significant" individuals were removed from their place within a loose chronological order and arranged alphabetically. Although this collection has been reprocessed and newly donated material has been integrated, the two systems of arrangement have been maintained since the original order is not clear.
  - Subseries II.1 Alphabetical, 1900-1983
    Subseries 1 is comprised of letters received by Trilling from his friends, family members, and business colleagues. Subjects covered ranged a variety of issues. Often Trilling debated current events with his colleagues, like an exchange concerning affirmative action with Daniel Patrick Moynihan. Many prominent writers may be found here such as Allen Ginsberg, who maintained a long correspondence with Trilling and often included drafts and ideas for poems in his letters, E.M. Forster, Robert Penn Warren (who Trilling affectionately referred to as "Red"), Saul Bellow, and e.e. cummings. In addition, there are long exchanges with John Crowe Ransom, with whom Trilling founded the School of English at Kenyon College, Henry Rosenthal, one of Trilling's oldest and closest friends, and Columbia History professor, Jacques Barzun who, along with being a close friend of Lionel Trilling, co-taught interdisciplinary courses with him. Letters from publishers, in particular Oxford University Press, Harvard University Press, and Viking Press illustrate the variety of professional literary relationships Trilling cultivated.
    Family correspondence is available with the following individuals: James Trilling, Diana Trilling, Fannie Trilling (mother), David Trilling (father), Harriet Schwartz (sister), and Hyman Trilling (uncle). In general there is very little correspondence of this nature within the collection.
    - A, 1931 February-1983 March (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Baldwin through Barzun, undated, 1933 October-1955 April (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Barzun through Bentley, undated, 1942 July-1975 November (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Beale through Butterfield, undated, 1931 October-1973 November (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Calkins through Chase, undated, 1929 April-1966 November (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Cherne through Cummings, undated, 1925-1964 September (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - D, undated, 1929 October-1975 October (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - E, undated, 1934 August-1974 May (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - F, undated, 1927 March-1974 August (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - G, undated, 1926 September-1928 August, 1945 November-1968 January (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - H, undated, 1931 August-1974 April (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - I through J, 1939 May-1974 February (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - K, undated, 1929 July-1974 April (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - L, undated, 1931 April-1961 December (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - M, undated, 1928 February-1973 November (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - N, undated, 1956 Septmber-1969 April (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - O, 1945 March-1969 March (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - P, undated, 1941 March-1975 October (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Publishers, 1947-1980, (3 Folders)
      - A through Macy (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - Martin through U (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - Viking Press (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Rahv through Ransom, undated, 1937-August-1957 October (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Riesman through Rosenthal, undated, 1947 June-1975 June (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Rosenthal, 1923 July-1926 November (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Rosenthal through Rukeyser, 1927 January-1970 April (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - S, 1927 November-1976 December (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - T, 1938 November-1971 November (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Trilling, David, undated, 1926 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Trilling, Diana to Trilling, Lionel, undated, 1929-1937, 1957 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Trilling, Fannie, 1953 August-1954 July, 1964 September-November (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Trilling, Harriet, undated, 1926 September-1927 May (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Trilling, Hyman to Trilling, David and Fannie, 1900-1901, 1919 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Trilling, James, 1957 January (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Trilling, Lionel to Trilling, Diana, undated, 1928 October-1931 July, (2 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Trilling, Lionel to Trilling, Diana, 1956 December-1962 May (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - U through V, 1940 June-1962 September (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - W though Z, 1929 October-1974 April (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Subseries II.2: Chronological, 1925-1976
    Letters held in Subseries 2 are similar in nature to those in Subseries 1. Correspondents include colleagues, publishers, personal friends, and students from Columbia University. Records concerning the Kenyon Institute, in particular the founding, the initial proposal, annual budget, and mission statement are found in January 1947. These letters are between Trilling, and fellow founders F.O. Matthieson and John Ransom. Many of the letters consist of requests to lecture at various academic institutions or to offer opinions of unpublished manuscripts. There are also letters from current and former students, many of whom were soldiers serving in Europe during World War II.
    - Undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - 1925 March-1931 November (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - 1932 May-1937 December (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - 1938 January-1939 May (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - 1939 June-1940 December (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - 1941 January-1942 June (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - 1942 July-1943 June (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - 1943 July-December (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - 1944 January-August (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - 1944 September-1945 March (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - 1945 April-September (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - 1945 October-1946 March (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - 1946 April-September (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - 1946 October-1947 March (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - 1947 April-September (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - 1947 October-November (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - 1947 December-1948 February (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - 1948 March-April (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - 1948 May-September (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - 1948 October-1949 February (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - 1949 February-March (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - 1949 April-August (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - 1950 January-1951 September (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - 1951 October-1952 April (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - 1952 May-December (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - 1953 January-March (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - 1953 April-September (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - 1953 October-December (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - 1954 January-April (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - 1954 May-July (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - 1954 August-November (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - 1954 December-1955 January (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - 1955 February-March (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - 1955 April-May (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - 1955 June-August (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - 1955 September-October (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - 1955 November-December (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - 1956 January-February (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - 1956 March-April (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - 1956 May-July (Box 17, Folder 3)